Okay, awesome question.
好的，很棒的问题。
Thanks for the pointing this out.
感谢你指出这个问题。
Sorry about that, everyone.
对不起，大家。
We have.
我们有。
Now, what are the rules for this year?
现在，今年的规则是什么？
Still, mostly,
仍然，大多数情况下，
this class will be remote.
这门课将以远程方式进行。
All lecture will be remote.
所有讲座将以远程方式进行。
This is where the department decided,
这是部门决定的地方。
actually early on,
实际上，在早期，
even before delta variant,
即使在 Delta 变种出现之前，
all exams will be remote,
所有考试将以远程方式进行。
will have three midterms.
将会有三次期中考试。
There is no final.
没有期末考试。
We have 17 discussion sections on thursday and fridays for on thursday,
我们在周四和周五有17个讨论小组，其中周四有...
13 on friday.
星期五的13号。
Out of those four will be in person.
其中四个将是面对面的。
There will be on friday,
星期五会有
and 30 will be remote.
其中30人将远程参与。
Now, please make sure because of that you have a working camera,
现在，请确保您有一台正常工作的摄像头，
because you are going to have zoom procuring of exams and require
因为你们将要进行远程考试，并且需要购买Zoom。
a section design reviews,
一节的设计审查
working with your colleagues for the group projects,
与你的同事一起合作完成团队项目，
all requires to see each other and also screen shots.
所有人都需要互相看到，并且还需要屏幕截图。
Goals of today lectures.
今天讲座的目标。
It's an introductory lecture, obviously,
这是一堂入门课程的讲座，显然地，
is to try to figure out a little bit what is an operating system.
是尝试弄清楚操作系统是什么的一点点内容。
And in particular, also, what is not.
特别是，还有什么不是。
And also,
而且，
i'm going to say a few words about what makes operating systems so exciting.
我将简要介绍一下什么使操作系统如此令人兴奋。
It's a while and is actually probably one of the excite most exciting times
这是一个相当长的时间，实际上可能是最令人兴奋的时刻之一。
to study and work on operating systems.
学习和工作于操作系统。
And then we are going to talk a little bit more at the end about how does
然后我们在最后会再多谈一点关于如何
the class operate.
这个班级运作。
Please,
请
interactivity is important.
互动性很重要。
Now I know that it's harder,
现在我知道这更难了，
especially with a weapon are i'm going to stop from time to time
特别是携带武器时，我会不时停下来。
and look and take questions.
并查看并回答问题。
Please ask questions and notes,
请提出问题和注意事项。
because even while I am talking,
因为即使我在说话的同时，
other people could answer them some of our t as
其他人可以回答他们一些我们的问题
what is fundamentally an operating system.
操作系统从根本上讲是什么？
One way to think about the operating system is that software layer,
一个思考操作系统的方式是将其视为软件层，
which runs on top of hardware of the hardware and provide support to the application.
操作系统运行在硬件之上，并为应用程序提供支持。
Right?
对吗？
Why does it mean providing support to applications?
为什么它意味着为应用程序提供支持？
Means that it makes it easier to develop applications on and take advantage
这意味着它使得在上面开发应用程序更加容易，并能充分利用其优势。
of the hardware capabilities.
硬件能力的一部分。
It also protects application from each others.
它还保护应用程序之间的相互影响。
It provides security and authentication,
它提供安全性和身份验证功能，
so only the applications which should a use a hardware and have access
只有需要使用硬件并具有访问权限的应用程序才能使用。
to the data,
对于数据，
and also provide support for cooperation.
并且提供合作支持。
There are applications which cooperate with each other.
有一些应用程序彼此合作。
Obviously, this is more and more expected today.
显然，这在今天越来越受到期望。
We are in the age of the internet.
我们正处于互联网时代。
Right?
对吗？
Why do we care to provide support for applications?
为什么我们关心为应用程序提供支持呢？
Because most of the things you do online,
因为你在网上做的大部分事情，
you do through applications.
你可以通过应用程序来实现。
That's it, right?
就是这样了，对吗？
It's the most a is a way people interact with computers is that people
这是人们与计算机互动的最常见方式之一
are going to interact with the virtual world.
将要与虚拟世界进行交互。
So you have physical world, virtual world,
所以你有物理世界和虚拟世界。
ritual or means application.
仪式或手段应用。
And also to drive home,
而且为了强调，
the.here are some numbers about how is a global mobile market size.
这里有一些关于全球移动市场规模的数字。
You can see it is huge.
你可以看到它非常巨大。
And actually,
实际上，
even year over year,
即使是年复一年，
the growth is significant about 20% or more.
增长幅度显著，约为20%或更高。
Right?
对吗？
It's, again, an application provides the abstraction,
这是一个再次提供抽象的应用程序。
manages the resources,
管理资源
harder resources.
更加困难的资源。
It's achieving that through using a bunch of algorithms for scheduling
它通过使用一系列调度算法来实现这一点。
application or processes.
应用程序或进程。
Providing access to resources from different concurrent applications
为不同并发应用程序提供资源访问
running at the same time
同时运行
and security and many more.
以及安全等等。
Right now,
现在，
let's look again a little bit.
让我们再仔细看一下。
There is a question here.
这里有一个问题。
What is now what is now an exciting,
现在是什么，现在是令人兴奋的。
why is now an exciting time for starting working hours?
为什么现在是开始工作的好时机？
We are going to answer that later,
我们稍后会回答这个问题。
because the impact of the os and the challenges are bigger than ever.
因为操作系统的影响和挑战比以往任何时候都更大。
That's a short answer.
这是一个简短的回答。
Here, again, it's not a problem during this lecture.
在这里，再次强调，在本次讲座中没有问题。
If you don't understand everything, this is pro.
如果你不理解一切，这是专业级别的。
We are aim here to provide some kind of end to end feeling about what
我们的目标是在这里提供一种端到端的感觉，让大家对什么
the operating system is doing.
操作系统正在做的事情。
But the rest of the class you are going to dive in.
但是你将要深入学习课程的其他内容。
We are going to look at all these aspects.
我们将会考虑所有这些方面。
I'm going to touch during this lecture in more detail.
在本讲座中，我将详细介绍这个问题。
Basically, again, it's an application.
基本上，再次强调，它是一个应用程序。
You want to run an application, run a program.
你想运行一个应用程序，运行一个程序。
You run to one, you have to run it on top of the harbor.
如果你追逐一个目标，你必须将其追到港口顶端。
Now,
现在，
what is a harder consisting from of?
"harder consisting from"这个短语在英文中并没有明确的意义。可能是由于拼写错误或语法错误导致的。请提供更多的上下文或修正错误，以便我能够帮助您更好地理解和翻译。
You have a processor needs to execute the instructions to run your applications,
你有一个处理器需要执行指令来运行你的应用程序。
and you clearly have a memory.
而且你显然有记忆力。
Right?
对吗？
We store the data and store the program.
我们存储数据和存储程序。
You store the application code.
你存储应用程序代码。
The processors read the instructions and read the data,
处理器读取指令并读取数据。
and executes those instructions on the data.
并且在数据上执行这些指令。
And this is how your application is running.
这是你的应用程序的运行方式。
In addition to just memory, you have a cache,
除了内存之外，你还有一个缓存。
keep the most recent data or the most access data around closer to the processor.
将最近的数据或最常访问的数据保持在离处理器更近的位置。
This for, obviously, for improving the performance,
这个目的显然是为了提高性能。
you have aa base table and tlb translation aside buffer this.
你有一个基本表和一个TLB（转换后备缓冲区）。
Again, it's are the mechanisms for improving the performance.
再次强调，这些机制是用于提高性能的。
Besides that,
除此之外，
you have aa storage where you need to store the data as a program at rest.
你有一个存储空间，需要将数据以程序的形式存储在其中。
The process and memory are storing the data and run the program
进程和内存负责存储数据并运行程序。
only when they are powered on.
只有当它们通电时才能工作。
Obviously, you have a lot of peripherals,
显然，你有很多外设设备。
you have displays,
你有显示器。
you have mouse,
你有鼠标。
you have network,
你有网络。
you are connected to the internet and many more.
你已连接到互联网，还有许多其他功能。
So this is quite complex.
这很复杂。
Right?
对吗？
Now, the key here,
现在，关键在于
and they are connected, right?
它们是连接在一起的，对吗？
All of these species are connected.
所有这些物种都是相互连接的。
The key here is basically how you are going to make easy and secure
关键在于你如何使其简单和安全。
for the application to run on this hardware and also take advantage
为了使应用程序在这台硬件上运行并充分利用其优势
of the hardware capabilities.
硬件能力的一部分。
And many of these things you learn like there's a machine structure
而且你学到的很多东西就像是一种机器结构
in cx 61 c it's,
在 CX 61 C 中，它是...
again,
再次，
one of the main functionality of the operating system is to abstract away
操作系统的主要功能之一是抽象化处理
this hardware to the application.
将这个硬件连接到应用程序中。
Let me, do I do this next set of few slides?
让我来，我接下来做这几张幻灯片好吗？
And then i'll stop for questions.
然后我会停下来等问题。
So one way to think about operating system is this like you lose honest.
操作系统的一种思考方式是，就像你失去了诚实一样。
Right?
对吗？
Why is that?
为什么这样做呢？
Because again,
因为再次，
it's provides this kind of abstraction of the physical resources.
它提供了对物理资源的这种抽象。
The abstractions are much easier to use and the applications
这些抽象更容易使用，应用程序也更简单
than the application using directly the harbor.
与直接使用港口的应用程序相比。
One of the way it makes it easier to use the operating system makes
它使操作系统更易于使用的一种方式是
easier for the application to use is removing limitations.
使应用程序更易于使用的方法是消除限制。
Right?
对吗？
For instance, it provides you the illusion to the eu being the application,
例如，它给你一种欧盟是应用程序的错觉。
the illusion that you are the only one,
你是唯一的幻觉
the application is the only one using that machine.
该应用程序是唯一使用该机器的应用程序。
It provides the illusion that the memory is like infinite.
它提供了一种假象，让内存看起来像是无限的。
There are no limits, right?
没有限制，对吗？
It provides the illusion, you have files,
它提供了一种错觉，让你觉得有文件存在。
and data stored in files.
以及存储在文件中的数据。
You have users, you have messages.
你有用户，你有消息。
So like,
所以，就像，
it's a much higher level of abstraction than operating just on beats.
这是比仅仅操作节拍更高层次的抽象。
And the main way the operating system provides abstracts.
操作系统提供抽象的主要方式是什么？
This resources,
这些资源，
harder resources to the application is through the process.
将更多的资源分配给应用程序的方法是通过进程。
The process is execution environment in which the applications run.
进程是应用程序运行的执行环境。
And the process consists of threads.
进程由线程组成。
This is basically the concept,
这基本上是概念。
the unit of execution.
执行单元。
It's our address space.
这是我们的地址空间。
This is a unit kind of allocates allocation, right?
这是一种单元分配的分配方式，对吗？
Allocate resources.
分配资源。
And you allocate addresses memory,
你分配内存地址，
and you have access to files and sockets to communicate over network.
你可以访问文件和套接字以进行网络通信。
The process encapsulate and provides all this abstraction to the application.
该进程封装并向应用程序提供所有这些抽象。
The application only need to understand about how to operate on threads,
该应用程序只需要了解如何操作线程即可。
another space, how to rewrite files,
另一个空间，如何重写文件？
how to communicate our sockets,
如何进行套接字通信
so to communicate our network.
所以要进行网络通信。
So that's it much easier.
所以这样就容易多了。
How does application take advantage?
应用程序如何利用？
You write the code and you compile the code.
你编写代码并编译代码。
Your code is not only the code you are writing,
你的代码不仅仅是你正在编写的代码，
but it's are going to use also libraries and a bunch of system libraries,
但它还将使用一些库和大量的系统库，
which are coming with any operating system.
这些都是随操作系统提供的。
Again, to summarize,
再次总结一下，
the application view of machine is that of the process.
机器的应用视图是进程的视图。
Each application program runs in its own process.
每个应用程序在自己的进程中运行。
This process provides this much, higher level,
这个过程提供了更高级别的功能。
much nicer interfaces, then they are harder.
更漂亮的界面通常意味着更难使用。
Okay?
好的？
It's again here you can see.
你可以再次看到它。
It's like I mentioned,
就像我之前提到的那样，
you have the program,
你有这个程序。
the code you write,
你写的代码
which is going to use some calls to the system libraries,
这将使用一些系统库的调用。
which are going basically to implement this api for this abstraction
将基本实现此抽象的API是哪些？
of our api its application programming interfaces,
我们的API是应用程序编程接口。
to manipulate these abstractions.
操作这些抽象。
And then you take care of this, you compile it,
然后你负责这个，你编译它，
you get the executable code and that you run it on your machine.
你得到了可执行代码，并在你的机器上运行它。
Let me stop here.
让我停在这里。
And let's see,
让我们看看，
there is a question.
有一个问题。
What else do you like the best?
你还喜欢什么其他的东西？
I think that's a good question.
我认为这是一个很好的问题。
I think, look,
我认为，看，
it's like you.
就像你一样。
I'm not going to surprise you here.
我不会在这里给你带来惊喜。
I think there are two systems which are quite good.
我认为有两个系统非常好。
It's and i'm using them.
我正在使用它们。
It's linux and macros.
这是关于Linux和宏的内容。
Mac west.
Mac西部。
We are going to talk about that.
我们将要讨论这个问题。
It's actually build also of the unique bsd which originated from berkeley.
它实际上也是由源自伯克利的独特的BSD构建的。
So,
所以，
okay,
好的，没问题。
so please ask questions and sorry,
所以请提问，抱歉，
again,
再次，
i've never used a minor.
我从未使用过次要设备。
We are using it because it's more scalable,
我们使用它是因为它更具可扩展性。
but is less interactive.
但是交互性较差。
So,
那么，
but we promise to improve on using these tools.
但我们承诺在使用这些工具上进行改进。
So excellent.
太棒了。
Again, just to summarize,
再次总结一下，
and i'm going to repeat a lot of things,
而且我会重复很多事情，
a lot of over and over again.
一次又一次的重复。
So hopefully i'm not going to borrow you,
希望我不会打扰你，
but there are actually not a lot of big concepts you are going to love
但实际上并没有很多你会喜欢的重要概念。
in this class,
在这门课中，
but the concepts are quite difficult and intricate it.
但是这些概念非常复杂和复杂。
And also because they are going to interpret and interact with each other.
而且因为它们将相互解释和交互。
But just to summarize,
但是为了总结一下，
a process consists of an address space,
一个进程由一个地址空间组成，
one or more thread.
一个或多个线程。
And this is the control,
这是控制部分，
the execution in that other space,
在那个其他空间中的执行
a bunch of other resources, like files,
一堆其他资源，比如文件，
sockets, and things like that.
套接字，以及类似的东西。
This is activity monitor.
这是活动监视器。
If you have a mac, if you go on here,
如果你有一台苹果电脑，如果你在这里打开，
you can look and you can see all these processes.
你可以查看并看到所有这些进程。
You can see, actually, the processes that tells you also,
你可以看到，实际上，这些进程也会告诉你，
I think the column probably i'm not sure you see my mouse,
我觉得这一列可能，我不确定你是否看到了我的鼠标。
but there is a column here called threats,
但是这里有一个名为"威胁"的列。
right?
对的？
This is unit of execution.
这是执行的单位。
Basically, for chrome, here,
基本上，对于Chrome，在这里，
you have 22 threads,
你有22个线程。
22 activities which are running concurrently in the same process.
在同一个进程中同时运行的22个活动。
Okay, so that's fine.
好的，那就没问题。
Again,
请再说一遍。
we obstructing away harder resources to the applications.
我们将更多的资源分配给应用程序。
It's one of the main main things
这是其中的主要事情之一
that the application is that the operating system is doing the main capabilities.
应用程序是操作系统的主要功能。
Now, less,
现在，less命令
we are going to look for other car.
我们打算去找其他的车。
We are going to go over the other capabilities as the operating system provides,
我们将会讨论操作系统提供的其他功能。
and to illustrate the need for the next one.
并且为下一个需求进行说明。
Now assume that you are going to have not only one program,
现在假设你不仅要运行一个程序，
but two programs to applications running on your machine.
但是在您的计算机上运行两个程序变成了两个应用程序。
And that every actually today,
而且，今天实际上每个人都这样。
almost every computer,
几乎每台计算机，
your laptop,
你的笔记本电脑，
your phone,
你的手机，
allows you to run multiple applications,
允许您同时运行多个应用程序，
which means multiple processes at the same time.
这意味着同时运行多个进程。
Right?
对吗？
This now,
现在，
the point is that it's, again,
关键是，再次强调的是，
it's like one of the abstractions.
这类似于抽象之一。
Remember that I mentioned that the operations operating system provides
记住我提到过操作系统提供的操作。
to the application is that
对于这个应用程序来说是这样的
provides the illusion of a dedicated machine.
提供了一个独立机器的幻觉。
Right?
对吗？
But now how you are going to do it when you are going to have
但是现在当你要进行时，你打算如何做呢？
multiple applications running at the same time,
同时运行多个应用程序
because they are going to run on the same hardware.
因为它们将在相同的硬件上运行。
Here is where it comes this kind of the other way you can look
这是另一种你可以看待问题的方式
at the operating system as a fairy,
作为一个操作系统的精灵，
because the only way you can provide the illusion of two applications,
是因为唯一的方法是提供两个应用程序的幻觉。
and each of them,
并且每一个人，
they have their own virtual machine.
他们有自己的虚拟机。
So to speak is to protect one of each other,
所谓相互保护，就是互相保护对方。
to isolate one of each other.
相互隔离。
Right?
对吗？
That's the only way here.
这是这里唯一的方法。
It's just,
只是，
let's go in a little bit more details to illustrate the need for that.
让我们更详细地讨论一下，以阐明对此的需求。
Now,
现在，
let's start with a processor.
让我们从处理器开始。
So you have only one processor,
所以你只有一个处理器，
and you have two applications,
而且你有两个应用程序，
and you have to run on the same processor.
并且你必须在同一处理器上运行。
At a given time, you can run on the processor,
在给定的时间内，你可以在处理器上运行。
only one application to give the illusion that both of them are going to run.
只需要一个应用程序就能让人产生两个都会运行的错觉。
They have their own machines.
他们有自己的机器。
So to speak,
可以这么说，
the way you do it is that you are going to divide the processor time
你要做的方式是将处理器时间分配。
in slots or slices.
在插槽或切片中。
Each slice, you have a different application running.
每个切片上都运行着不同的应用程序。
The slices are a few million seconds.
这些切片是几百万秒。
1 millisecond, 10 millisecond things like is something like that.
1 毫秒，10 毫秒这样的东西就是这样的。
Right?
对吗？
In this particular example,
在这个特定的例子中，
you have the brown application running.
你的应用程序正在运行。
If you can see here,
如果你能看到这里，
the processor access is a memory,
处理器访问内存。
which is in the process allocated to the brown process one.
这是分配给棕色进程一的进程。
It read it reads a code and executes that code.
它读取并执行一段代码。
Is there for running program on?
是否有可运行的程序？
Right?
对吗？
But now,
但是现在，
next,
接下来，
you will also have program two, support.
你还将拥有程序二的支持。
Program two in memory,
将程序二加载到内存中，
also have some piece of,
还有一些部分，
you also have some piece of memory which is allocated to process,
你还有一些分配给进程的内存空间。
right?
是的，没错。
At some point,  Right?
在某个时候，对吗？
You run at some..
你以某种速度奔跑..
Now.
现在。
I said after a little bit of time,
经过一小段时间后，我说道，
you allocate to program one to run.
你分配给程序一来运行。
Now you are going to switch the program, too.
现在你也要切换程序了。
You are going to run.
你要开始跑步了。
And by doing so and switching at a very high frequency,
通过这样做并以非常高的频率进行切换，
you give the evening is an illusion to each of these applications that it's
你给这些应用程序的晚上是一个幻觉
using the computer allowed.
允许使用计算机。
Right?
对吗？
Now, the problem here, if you can see, for instance,
现在，问题在于，如果你能看到的话，例如，
if you look at the memory,
如果你查看内存，
you're having the same memory,
你们拥有相同的内存空间。
physical memory.
物理内存。
You have the data from multiple applications,
你拥有来自多个应用程序的数据，
and they have to to read and write the data.
他们必须读取和写入数据。
Right?
对吗？
And certainly,
当然，
you do not want,
你不想要。
say, in this case,
在这种情况下，
a program to our process to read or even more to write the data in process on.
一个程序可以让我们的进程读取甚至写入进程中的数据。
Right?
对吗？
You also don't run the any process store for that matter.
你也不需要运行任何进程存储。
Of fact, any process to write to modify the operating system memory.
实际上，任何进程都可以写入或修改操作系统内存。
Right?
对吗？
Because then the operating system may crash.
因为这样操作系统可能会崩溃。
If you write up an application,
如果你写了一个应用程序，
modify the operating system in memory.
在内存中修改操作系统。
And also you need to be careful with the storage.
你还需要注意存储空间。
Right?
对吗？
You shouldn't allow one program,
你不应该允许一个程序，
two of one user to modify the data of another users,
一个用户修改了另一个用户的数据。
especially if that data is private or read it.
尤其是当数据是私密的或需要读取时。
Okay?
好的？
So this is what we mean.
这就是我们的意思。
Now you need to you protect protection,
现在你需要保护自己的安全。
so you need to protect one application,
所以你需要保护一个应用程序，
one process from another.
一个进程从另一个进程中创建。
You need to protect one process from the operating system,
你需要保护一个进程免受操作系统的干扰。
and protect the operating system from the process.
并保护操作系统免受进程的影响。
Right?
对吗？
When an application on a program tries to execute some of these actions,
当程序中的应用程序尝试执行其中一些操作时，
which are precluded like accessing the data of the memory,
被禁止的操作包括访问内存中的数据，
which belongs to another process,
它属于另一个进程。
or accessing the memory belongs to the operating system.
或者访问属于操作系统的内存。
The operating system,
操作系统，
one way is going to deal with this offending application,
一种方法是处理这个冒犯的应用程序，
is crashing the processing segmentation fault.
正在崩溃处理分段错误。
But it's, again,
但是，再一次，
the main point here is that in order to create this illusion of to
这里的主要观点是，为了营造这种错觉，我们需要
a process that they are using the machine alone,
一个独自使用机器的进程
you need to isolate and to protect processes from each other.
你需要将进程隔离并保护它们相互之间的安全。
Also,
另外，
in order to make sure that the operating system itself is not crashes a as
为了确保操作系统本身不会崩溃
a result,
结果，
processes modifying operating system data,
修改操作系统数据的进程，
then we need also to isolate the operating system itself from the processes.
那么我们还需要将操作系统本身与进程隔离开来。
Right?
对吗？
Let's see.
让我们看看。
I was looking at the question,
我正在看这个问题，
why is a good time for learning oils right now?
为什么现在是学习油画的好时机？
It's again, we are going stick around until for the next half an hour or.
好的，我们会再等待半个小时左右。
So so now,
所以现在，
the last way we can look at the operating system is like a glue.
我们可以将操作系统看作是一种胶水的最后一种方式。
Right?
对吗？
Why is that?
为什么这样做呢？
Again,
请再说一遍。
it's very logic, right?
这很合乎逻辑，对吗？
Illogical.
不合逻辑的。
First,
首先，
you need to abstract those harder to make it
你需要将那些较难的内容进行抽象化处理
much easier for the application developers to write applications.
这使得应用程序开发人员编写应用程序变得更加容易。
Second,
其次，
you need to provide protection, isolations,
你需要提供保护和隔离功能。
because typically, you are going to have multiple applications,
因为通常情况下，您会有多个应用程序。
multiple processes,
多个进程
sharing the same part.
共享同一部分。
And the final part is that these applications or some applications
最后一部分是这些应用程序或一些应用程序
are communicating with each other.
正在彼此通信。
So you need to provide some kind of glue between them to provide
所以你需要提供一种粘合剂来连接它们以提供
some common services.
一些常见的服务。
This is coming the form of networking or storage.
这是关于网络或存储的问题。
You can application can communicate through files,
你的应用程序可以通过文件进行通信。
one application write in a files,
一个应用程序写入一个文件中，
another application read from a file.
另一个应用程序从文件中读取。
Obviously, this also comes with authorization and things like that.
显然，这也涉及到授权和类似的事情。
But this is where you can think about the operating system as a glue.
但这就是你可以将操作系统视为胶水的地方。
Right?
对吗？
They need to provide the communications,
他们需要提供通信设备。
enable you the ability to share the resources.
使您能够共享资源的能力。
And again,
再次，
the common the operating system is doing that by providing these common services,
常见的操作系统通过提供这些常见服务来实现这一点。
file systems, networking,
文件系统，网络
so forth.
等等。
I'm going to stop here.
我要停在这里了。
Are there any questions?
有任何问题吗？
One question is,
一个问题是，
what are the methods that allow different processes to talk with each other?
允许不同进程之间进行通信的方法有哪些？
I know your socket communication.
我知道你的套接字通信。
It's a valid method.
这是一个有效的方法。
So there are a few of them,
所以有几个问题，
and we are going to learn about them.
我们将要学习它们。
One is me soccer communication,
一个是我足球交流。
so it's like networking.
所以它就像网络一样。
Right?
对吗？
You can communicate with each other to processes whether they are
你可以通过进程间通信来相互交流，无论它们是什么类型的进程。
on the same machine or different machines,
在同一台机器上或不同的机器上，
through sockets, through a network interface.
通过套接字，通过网络接口。
The processes which are on the same machine,
在同一台机器上的进程
they can also communicate through share memory.
它们还可以通过共享内存进行通信。
You can also have the ability to communicate with share memory.
你还可以通过共享内存进行通信的能力。
And also, like I mentioned earlier,
而且，正如我之前提到的，
you can communicate through storage.
你可以通过存储进行通信。
An application can write a piece of data on the store on the local file system,
一个应用程序可以将一段数据写入本地文件系统的存储空间。
or even for a global file system.
甚至可以用于全局文件系统。
And others application can read.
其他应用程序也可以读取。
Okay?
好的？
Is a processor just what we call a cpu?
处理器就是我们所说的中央处理器（CPU）吗？
For most cases, these are interchangeable,
在大多数情况下，这两者是可以互换的。
although we are also going to call processor like specialized, harder,
虽然我们也会将处理器称为专用、更难的设备，
specialized processors,
专用处理器
several.
几个。
So it's a little bit broader,
所以它稍微更广泛一些，
but unless has a right specified the equivalence.
但是除非有明确指定的等价性，否则不会执行。
Ha ha ha.
哈哈哈。
Will adam replace x 86 in consumer space?
亚当架构会在消费者领域取代x86吗？
Ii it's clear that autumn has a lot of momentum right now.
很明显，秋天现在有很大的势头。
One example,
一个例子，
obviously, it's m one from apple.
显然，这是来自苹果公司的产品。
You see that become more and more proud, powerful,
你会发现越来越自豪、强大，
but there are also arm starts to be deployed in data centers.
但是现在也开始在数据中心部署 ARM 架构的服务器。
Actually, there is one new instance which from amazon called graviton.
实际上，亚马逊推出了一种名为Graviton的新实例。
This is around armed processor.
这是关于武装处理器的内容。
And it's quite fast.
而且它非常快速。
It's actually his very good performance and is cheaper.
实际上，这是他非常出色的表现，并且价格更便宜。
Now, we'll see, right?
现在，我们就看看，对吧？
Because what intel is going to do,
因为英特尔将要做的事情，
clearly, they announce a bunch of initiatives,
显然，他们宣布了一系列的举措，
but adam,
但是亚当，
it's has a lot of momentum at this..
这个在这方面有很大的动力..
Let me go here.
让我过去这里。
There is something about visualization.
关于可视化有一些内容。
There is something about there are a few more questions here.
这里有几个问题。
Let me ask answer them.
让我来回答它们。
It's one question on the chap.
这是第几章的一个问题。
By the way, please try to ask question for on q and a so I have one source.
顺便说一下，请尽量在问答环节提出问题，这样我就有一个信息来源了。
I can read them from.
我可以读取它们。
So there's a lot of there are some comments about vmy about visualization.
关于虚拟化的问题，有一些关于vmy的评论。
We are going to talk about visualization even a little bit during this lecture.
在本讲座中，我们将稍微谈一下可视化。
But visualization is a way to provide the illusion to every process
但是可视化是一种为每个进程提供幻觉的方式。
to every application that they are using.
对于他们使用的每个应用程序。
They're using alone the machine.
他们独自使用这台机器。
There is another question about risk five.
关于 Risk-V 的问题还有一个。
This obviously was done at berkeley.
这显然是在伯克利完成的。
I think these five it's has a great future.
我认为这五个项目有着很好的前景。
And for those of you don't know,
对于那些不知道的人，
at least five is an open instruction set architecture,
至少有五个是开放指令集架构。
which means that you don't need to pay any license to use it,
这意味着您使用它时不需要支付任何许可费。
to build process to build processors around it.
构建围绕它的处理器的过程。
In contrast, arm for arm,
相比之下，一臂对一臂，
you need to pay life license in order to use and to provide the art
您需要支付终身许可费才能使用和提供这些艺术作品。
of instruction set.
指令集
But risk five.
但是风险很高。
Now it's targeting internet of things or mobile devices, very low power.
现在它的目标是物联网或移动设备，非常低功耗。
This is how they started,
这是他们的起点，
but this is the way they are started.
但这是它们启动的方式。
So you'll see maybe a risk.
所以你可能会看到一些风险。
There is a chance that are going to follow the trajectory of arm.
有可能会跟随臂的轨迹。
And it can become for arm what arm is for into.
它可以成为 ARM 对于 Into 的那样的 ARM。
But again, it's obvious this is in the future,
但是再次强调，显然这是在未来发生的事情，
but obviously,
但显然，
it has a lot of promise.
它有很大的潜力。
I'm going to go back now to the lecture slides.
我现在要回到讲义幻灯片了。
Again,
请再说一遍。
this is give examples about some of the services which are provided
这是关于一些提供的服务的示例。
by the operating system.
由操作系统完成。
We didn't discuss so far.
我们到目前为止还没有讨论过。
And some of the management services and does the operating system provides,
操作系统提供了一些管理服务，包括：
and maybe you do not think right away to them.
也许你不会立刻想到它们。
It's like power management,
这类似于电源管理，
correct?
正确吗？
Or especially for mobile devices,
特别是针对移动设备，
you need to manage the power.
你需要管理电源。
And across the application,
在整个应用程序中，
if you have an application which user is proportionate amount of battery,
如果你有一个应用程序会消耗用户相应的电池电量，
maybe you want to isolate to protect other applications from that.
也许你想要隔离以保护其他应用程序。
You need to manage a network.
你需要管理一个网络。
You need to manage almost every shared resource,
你需要管理几乎所有的共享资源，
right?
对的？
When I I referred shared by multiple applications.
当我被多个应用程序引用时。
So in summary,
总结一下，
it's, again,
又是，
repeating.
重复。
There are three things.
有三件事情。
An operating system is doing.
操作系统是一种软件，它管理计算机硬件和软件资源，并提供用户与计算机系统之间的接口。它负责协调和控制计算机的各个组件，以确保系统的正常运行。操作系统的主要功能包括进程管理、内存管理、文件系统管理、设备驱动程序管理和用户界面管理等。它还提供了一些基本的服务和工具，如调度程序、内存分配器、文件系统和网络协议栈等，以支持应用程序的运行和用户的操作。总之，操作系统是计算机系统中不可或缺的核心组件，它使计算机能够高效地运行和管理各种任务。
One is providing a clean easy to use abstractions of the physical resources
其中之一是提供对物理资源的清晰易用的抽象化。
to the application,
至于应用程序，
make it much easier for application developers to develop this application.
使应用程序开发人员更容易开发这个应用程序。
And this means like you can think about this,
这意味着你可以考虑一下这个问题，
like is like you lose your list,
喜欢就像你失去了清单一样
then which follows from providing clean abstractions.
这是提供清晰抽象的结果。
You can think about operating system as a referee.
你可以将操作系统视为一名裁判。
And in this case,
在这种情况下，
the operating system provides protection and isolation of shared resources across
操作系统提供了对共享资源的保护和隔离。
for multiple applications.
用于多个应用程序。
Right?
对吗？
We share those resources.
我们共享这些资源。
And the final is that it's a glue that operating system provides common
最终的结果是，操作系统提供了一个常见的粘合剂。
services in particularly also enables this application to communicate
特别是服务，还使得该应用程序能够进行通信。
to each other.
彼此之间。
So now,
所以现在，
let's talk a little bit more about cs one city to,
让我们再多谈谈关于CS One City的事情吧。
in general,
一般来说，
and then talk a little bit about why now and why it's exciting and challenging.
然后稍微谈谈为什么现在进行这项工作，以及为什么它令人兴奋和具有挑战性。
Why take cs on ct two?
为什么要在计算机科学专业上修读计算机操作系统课程？
It's again,
又是这样，
because some of you will actually design and build operating system
因为你们中的一些人将会设计和构建操作系统。
or components of them like file systems,
或者它们的组成部分，比如文件系统，
right?
对的吗？
You go to google,
你去谷歌搜索。
you may work on android.
你可以在Android上工作。
For instance, you go like apple,
例如，你可以说像苹果一样。
you may or microsoft,
你可以选择微软或者其他公司。
you may work on their operating systems,
你可能会在他们的操作系统上工作，
or if you are to any company which depend running its software on linux,
或者如果你是任何依赖于在Linux上运行其软件的公司的一员，
you might work on linux to provide new capabilities for the applications
你可以在Linux上工作，为应用程序提供新的功能。
that are important for your company.
对于您的公司而言，这些是重要的。
But many of you are going to build software which run on top
但是你们中的许多人将要构建运行在上面的软件
of the operating systems.
操作系统的种类。
And to build better software,
为了构建更好的软件，
you need to understand how the operating system was working.
你需要理解操作系统是如何工作的。
You need to understand to the concepts.
你需要理解这些概念。
That's what it is.
就是这样。
So next,
接下来，
i'm going to talk about what makes operating system exciting and challenging.
我将要谈论的是什么使操作系统变得令人兴奋和具有挑战性。
Let me check again for the questions.
让我再检查一下问题。
How can application interact with these common services
应用程序如何与这些常见服务进行交互？
through the api application programming interfaces?
通过应用程序编程接口（API）？
I mentioned a little bit in passing earlier on.
我之前只是顺便提到了一点。
These are exposed by system libraries.
这些是由系统库公开的。
Right?
对吗？
For instance, if you want to access a file,
例如，如果你想访问一个文件，
you are going to have an api to access that file, read, write,
你将拥有一个API来访问该文件，进行读取和写入操作。
seek the same for sending our communication,
寻求相同的方式来发送我们的通信，
sending and receiving data.
发送和接收数据。
You are going to have another api and this is exposed
你将会有另一个API，并且这个API是公开的。
by these system libraries and implement it.
通过这些系统库来实现它。
Why does searching for files from windows?
为什么要从Windows中搜索文件？
File explorer for this feels super slow?
这个文件浏览器感觉非常慢？
Unfortunately, I don't know.
很抱歉，我不知道。
Ii have no answer to that question,
我对这个问题没有答案。
but if you get the answer,
但是如果你得到了答案，
i'll be interested in the answer.
我对答案感兴趣。
In short, what makes the system,
简而言之，系统的特点有哪些？
the operating system?
操作系统？
Now,
现在，
extremely exciting is because there are many things happen.
非常令人兴奋的原因是因为发生了许多事情。
In the next few slides,
在接下来的几张幻灯片中，
i'm going to tell you what happens.
我将告诉你发生了什么事情。
And these things actually makes operating systems,
这些事情实际上构成了操作系统，
addressing the operating system problems more difficult,
解决操作系统问题更加困难
and hopefully more rewarding once you solve the problems.
一旦你解决了问题，希望会更有回报。
So as you probably know,
正如你可能知道的，
i'm sure everyone heard that many times for the more than 50 years,
我确定大家在过去50多年中听过这句话很多次了。
all our industry,
我们所有的行业，
hardware industry, software industry,
硬件行业，软件行业
and large part was really driven by the morsel.
而且很大一部分确实是由这块小块驱动的。
Machines are harder,
机器更难操作，
becoming more and more powerful, very fast.
变得越来越强大，速度非常快。
So according to gordon moore,
根据戈登·摩尔的说法，
who was a co founder of intel,
英特尔的联合创始人是谁？
in 65,
在65年中，
he predicted that the transistor density of semiconductor chips will double
他预测半导体芯片的晶体管密度将翻倍。
roughly every 2 years.
大约每两年一次。
There's a morse law, right?
是的，有摩尔定律。
And you have this plus here.
你在这里有一个加号。
You see a line,
你看到一条线。
but you have see a line on the x axis is a time on the y axis.
但是你在x轴上看到的是时间，在y轴上。
It's the performance or the number of transistors.
这是性能或晶体管数量的问题。
And you have a line y because the y axis is in log scale.
而且你有一条y轴线，因为y轴是以对数刻度显示的。
Now,
现在，
morris law says the transistor density doubles roughly every 2 years.
摩尔定律指出，晶体管密度大约每两年翻倍一次。
So on the same area,
在同一区域上，
you can cram twice as many transistors.
你可以将两倍的晶体管塞进去。
This leads to the performance of the processor doubling roughly every 18 months.
这导致处理器性能大约每18个月翻倍一次。
Why discrepancy?
为什么存在差异？
The discrepancy is?
差异是什么？
Because since the transistors are becoming closer to each other,
由于晶体管之间的距离越来越近，
the latency between transistors to communicate between transistors decreases.
晶体管之间的通信延迟减小了。
And therefore, you have double reasons you have that are these compounds
因此，你有双重理由拥有这些化合物。
to increasing the transistor density.
增加晶体管密度。
And therefore,
因此，
the performance increases a little bit faster,
性能提升速度稍微快一点，
or used to increase a little bit faster.
或者用于稍微加快速度。
The challenge is that the modest law ended.
挑战在于适度的法律已经结束。
Okay?
好的？
This again,
又是这个问题，
it shows here is a performance versus time the performance
这里显示的是性能随时间的变化情况，即性能与时间的关系。
of a single court for processor.
一个处理器的单个核心
And between 1995 and2002 or 2003,
在1995年和2002年或2003年之间，
this was what you see here is green.
你在这里看到的是绿色的。
This is the golden age,
这是黄金时代，
so to speak,
可以这么说，
because in this period,
因为在这个时期，
but 4 months increased,
但是增加了4个月。
doubled every 18 months,
每18个月翻一倍。
or increase 52% of the year.
或者增长52%的年份。
And the problem right now is that this performance will call increasing
目前的问题是性能会不断增加。
just a few percent every year.
每年只有几个百分点。
So this is a big problem.
这是一个很大的问题。
Why it is a big problem,
为什么这是一个大问题？
because at that time,
因为那个时候，
when the capabilities of a single core basically are no longer increasing,
当单个核心的能力基本上不再增加时，
the demands of the new applications are increasing faster than ever.
新应用的需求增长速度比以往任何时候都要快。
Here,
在这里，
it's a plot open.
这是一个情节开放的情节。
I plot.
我绘图。
Many of you may have seen it.
你们中的许多人可能已经看过了。
And it shows Compute cup requirements to train the state of the art models.
它展示了训练最先进模型所需的计算资源要求。
This is plot was going back to 2012 was published in 2019.
这个情节是回溯到2012年，于2019年出版。
Again, it's a lot of scale.
再次强调，这是一个很大的规模。
If you look here,
如果你看这里，
this growth is absolutely astounding.
这种增长绝对令人震惊。
The requirements,
要求，
computer requirements grew 35 times every 18 months.
计算机需求每18个月增长35倍。
I added here another data point for 2020.
我在这里添加了2020年的另一个数据点。
A new model was released.
发布了一个新的型号。
If you remember a little more than 1 year ago,
如果你还记得一年多前的事情，
gpt three from open ai made a lot of waves.
OpenAI的GPT-3引起了很大的轰动。
It has 175,
它有175个。
55 million parameters.
5500万个参数。
And again, it fits a curve.
而且，它适合一条曲线。
This, again, is not only as aesthetic models.
这不仅仅是美学模型。
You have models like with the gpt three is actually language model,
你们有像GPT-3这样的模型，实际上是语言模型。
video model,
视频模型
pattern recognition,
模式识别
and things like that.
等等，诸如此类的东西。
And now here is a morse law.
现在我给你介绍一下摩尔定律。
Actually, it's a morse law.
实际上，这是摩尔定律。
Even forget that it ended,
甚至忘记它已经结束了，
even if it were intended,
即使有意这样做，
a we would be in a big trouble.
如果我们这样做，我们会陷入大麻烦中。
But it ended.
但它结束了。
And this is actually how the morse law looked like.
这实际上就是摩尔定律的样子。
You see, is a gap.
你看，这是一个间隙。
This is huge, and this is explanation.
这是巨大的，这是解释。
It's, again, the law a you have a log scale here.
这里使用了对数刻度，这是法律要求的。
And the gap increases exponentially every year or every day if you want.
而且这个差距每年或每天都在呈指数增长。
So now what do you do about it?
那么现在你打算怎么办呢？
Right?
对吗？
You heard about specialized processors.
你听说过专用处理器吗？
You have gp us like and media,
你有GPUS、喜欢和媒体。
gpsa 100 is the latest on dp us from ten several processor units from google,
gpsa 100是谷歌最新的处理器单元之一，具有十个处理器单元。
sarah brass.
莎拉·布拉斯。
This is a company building huge chips,
这是一家制造巨大芯片的公司。
very powerful.
非常强大。
And any of everyone else builds their own version of gpu intel alchemist,
而其他每个人都可以构建自己的版本的英特尔Alchemist GPU。
your announcement,
你的公告，
md radium, and so forth.
镭，等等。
The main idea here,
这里的主要思想是
obviously,
显然，
we specialize harder is that you are going to narrow the workloads you
我们更专注的意思是你将要缩小工作负载范围
want to support,
想要提供支持，
because of that,
因此，
more about that workload.
关于那个工作负载的更多信息。
So you can do more optimization,
所以你可以进行更多的优化。
and you can be smarter in the way you design the chip.
而且你可以在设计芯片的方式上更聪明一些。
You increase the parallelism and things like that.
你增加并行性和类似的东西。
So you can make it much faster for that workload than a general purpose processor,
因此，对于该工作负载，您可以比通用处理器更快地完成任务。
right?
对的？
But now you need to program these things as well.
但是现在你也需要编写这些程序。
You may need to share these things as well.
你可能还需要分享这些东西。
Right?
对吗？
And they are going to be quite different from the cp us.
它们将与计算机处理器相当不同。
And who has to deal with that.
那要由谁来处理呢？
As big as stand,
就像一个巨大的展台一样，
your operating system has to be with it.
你的操作系统必须与之兼容。
Now, the problem is that even with this specialized hardware,
现在的问题是，即使有这种专门的硬件，
they help,
它们有帮助。
obviously, there are more powerful than a single call,
显然，有更强大的功能超过单个调用。
but still,
但是，
they don't close the gap.
他们没有填补这个差距。
Here,
在这里，
it's the performance of the gp os and of the tp os on the same on the same block.
这是关于GP操作系统和TP操作系统在相同块上的性能表现。
And there is a start here, basically same.
这里也有一个开始，基本上是一样的。
We are assuming in order to make sense and to normalize.
我们假设是为了理解和规范化。
Typically, aspect,
通常，方面，
in particular, based on open ai data,
特别是基于OpenAI的数据，
the utilization of the hardware by this,
这个的硬件利用率
the state of the art training algorithms is like 33%.
最先进的训练算法的准确率大约为33%。
When I show the performance of the gp us and dp us here,
在这里展示GPU和CPU的性能时，
I am factoring it for that utilization.
我正在为其利用率进行因式分解。
So that's huge problem, right?
那是一个很大的问题，对吗？
Even with the cp us and gp us,
即使有中央处理器和图形处理器，
and is a memory demands are growing as fast, even faster.
随着时间的推移，内存需求正在迅速增长，甚至更快。
Here,
在这里，
it's a log scale is a number of parameters of these models.
这是一个对这些模型参数的对数刻度。
This is from 2016.
这是来自2016年的信息。
And now the last.is,
现在是最后一个了。
this is from china.
这是来自中国的消息。
And this is1.70 55 trillion parameters.
这是1.70 55万亿个参数。
So it's 10 times larger than gpt three.
所以它比GPT-3大10倍。
I'm sure you are going to hear about other announcement,
我相信你很快就会听到其他的公告。
even bigger models.
更大的模型。
If you plot and if you look at this data, it's again itself, again,
如果你绘制并查看这些数据，你会发现它再次是自身。
lock scale.
锁定比例尺。
Although it may not look like,
尽管它可能看起来不像，
since 2016,
自2016年以来，
the size of this model increased 40 times,
这个模型的大小增加了40倍。
every 18 months.
每18个月。
And if you look at the last 3 years,
如果你看过去的三年，
300, 40 times.
300，40次。
Right?
对吗？
This is phenomenal.
这太棒了。
During this time,
在这段时间内，
the gpu memory,
GPU内存
1.7 x every 18 months.
每18个月增长1.7倍。
It used to be not a few years back.
几年前还不是这样的。
Right?
对吗？
In 2017, eighteen,
2017年，十八岁
you can feed the largest models on a single gpu now,
现在你可以在单个GPU上运行最大的模型了。
you need more than 1,000 gp us to just to store the parameters
你需要超过1,000美元的GP来仅仅存储这些参数。
of the largest models.
最大的模型之一。
So let's see,
那么让我们来看一下，
what are the other trends?
其他趋势有哪些？
Now let's move to storage capacity.
现在让我们来讨论存储容量。
Storage capacity is still growing exponentially.
存储容量仍在呈指数增长。
The one thing here,
这里的一件事，
it used to be dominating the storage by harvest drives no longer.
它曾经通过收割驱动器来主导存储，但现在不再如此。
Now you have more and more solid state devices.
现在你拥有越来越多的固态设备。
You can see here, the capacity of a solid,
你可以在这里看到，固体的容量
a a solid state drive started to exceed in 2015, 16.
2015年和2016年开始，固态硬盘开始大幅增长。
That of the so the biggest ssd drive exceeded the capacity of the biggest
最大的SSD驱动器的容量超过了最大容量。
harvest drive around to fifteen to 6 to 16.
将收获车开到15号，然后到6号，最后到16号。
And today, if you are looking the largest ssd3.5 inch drive,
今天，如果你正在寻找最大的3.5英寸SSD驱动器，
it's 100 terabytes.
这是100太字节。
The largest ssd is 18 terabytes.
最大的固态硬盘容量为18TB。
Now,
现在，
you are going to pay dearly for this 100 terabyte ssd drive.
你将为这个100TB固态硬盘付出巨大代价。
It costs 40 k is 400 per terabytes.
每个 terabyte 的成本是 40k，即每个 terabyte 的成本是 400。
While to get 18 terabytes, they say,
他们说，要获得18TB的存储空间，
sorry, this is hardest drive.
抱歉，这是最困难的驱动器。
I'm going to just correct this one.
我只需要纠正这一个。
For that, you pay only $600,
对此，您只需支付600美元。
a 33 dull pet terabytes.
一个33寸的无聊宠物硬盘。
Now,
现在，
you can have more economical or economical choices when you look at the ss ds,
当您查看SS DS时，您可以有更经济或经济的选择。
like, for instance,
例如，比如说，
if you under four terabytes ssd it costs $95 better up.
如果你购买四TB的固态硬盘，价格为95美元，建议你升级。
Terabyte still more expensive than the harvest stripes.
1TB的存储容量仍然比收获条纹更昂贵。
Despite of this,
尽管如此，
the ss ds are winning the war.
SS和DS正在赢得战争。
There is little question about that.
这一点几乎没有疑问。
Why?
为了帮助更多的学生理解和学习计算机操作系统课程，我将英文内容翻译成中文。这样可以让更多的学生受益并提高他们的学习效果。
Because the hardest drive are cheaper,
因为硬盘更便宜。
but they are much slower.
但它们速度要慢得多。
Sometimes between ten x and 100 x consumes much more power,
有时候在10倍和100倍之间的消耗更多电力。
very important for data center and mobile devices or laptops.
对于数据中心和移动设备或笔记本电脑来说非常重要。
And they are less reliable.
而且它们不太可靠。
These are some projections to make to drive home that point
以下是一些投影片，用于强调这一点
on the left hand side.
在左手边。
It's about, you can see different technologies is projected up to 2030.
这是关于到2030年不同技术的展望。
You can have here with dark blue is ss ds with light blue.
你可以将这里的深蓝色换成浅蓝色。
It's a flash.
这是一个闪存。
So this is usb the storage in your camera and things like that.
这是用于相机等设备的USB存储设备。
And then the yellow is actually our tapes.
然后黄色实际上是我们的磁带。
So all the technology,
所以所有的技术，
probably many of you have never seen a tape,
可能你们中的许多人从未见过磁带，
but they are very cheap.
但它们非常便宜。
That's why.
这就是为什么。
And then o is dark orange or with orange is actually harvest lives.
然后o是深橙色或者橙色，实际上是收获的象征。
Also, the same study anticipate that in 2026, actually,
同样的研究预测，实际上在2026年，
the ss ds will be cheaper per terabytes and hardest drives.
SSD和硬盘的价格将会更便宜，每个TB的存储容量也会更大。
And that's why probably you are going to see on the left hand side,
这就是为什么你可能会在左手边看到的原因。
a point in around 2025 after which the market share of and
在2025年左右的一个时间点之后，市场份额将开始下降
not only of the harvest drive is going to decrease.
不仅收成将会减少。
Networking still going very fast.
网络仍然非常快速。
Today you can have 100 garbage connections to your machines in aws next
今天你可以在AWS上拥有100个垃圾连接到你的机器上。
will be probably 400 garbage per second.
每秒可能会产生大约400个垃圾。
There are other factors, right?
还有其他因素，对吗？
It's like,
就像是，
for instance,
例如，
another important aspect is the fact that it used to be early on.
另一个重要的方面是它曾经是早期的。
You have very, few huge computer computers.
你们有非常少的大型计算机。
They are extremely expensive,
它们非常昂贵。
tens of millions of dollars.
数千万美元。
In that case, you have a lot of people using the same machine.
在这种情况下，你有很多人使用同一台机器。
Right?
对吗？
Actually, in 60s, if I remember correct or 50s,
实际上，在60年代，如果我记得正确的话，或者是50年代，
when ibm started the to to build computers,
当IBM开始建造计算机时，
watson,
是的，有什么我可以帮助您的吗？
who was the founder of the ibm and the ceo was saying that he
IBM的创始人是谁？CEO曾经说过什么？
doesn't believe that there is a need,
不相信有这个必要
then for more than five or six computers in the entire united states.
那么在整个美国境内超过五六台计算机的情况下。
Of course, over time,
当然，随着时间的推移，
the computers have proliferated becomes smaller and smaller.
计算机的数量越来越多，而且体积也越来越小。
It used to be probably in 2000s.
这可能是在2000年代的时候。
At the end of the previous century,
在上个世纪末，
you have one user, one computer.
你有一个用户，一个计算机。
And now you have a user.
现在你有一个用户了。
One user is many computers, right?
一个用户可以使用多台计算机，对吗？
If you're in your car alone,
如果你独自一人在车里，
you have ten and send ten of cp us.
你有十个并发送十个CP给我们。
Right?
对吗？
So this change,
所以这个改变，
and as you can imagine,
正如你可以想象的那样，
this also is going to impact the way you are going to design the operating system.
这也将影响你将要设计操作系统的方式。
There is another aspect here.
这里还有另一个方面。
There is an extreme range of time scales.
时间尺度有非常广泛的范围。
This is from jeff dean of google,
这是来自谷歌的Jeff Dean的消息。
very influential computer scientist,
非常有影响力的计算机科学家
build many of the distributed systems there.
在那里构建许多分布式系统。
If you look about from an application and the operating system,
如果你从应用程序和操作系统的角度来看，
you have to deal with a latency as low as lower than normal.
你需要处理一个比正常情况下更低的延迟。
No, second, this is l one cash, this is a cash,
不，第二个是l一个现金，这是一个现金。
which is the first level cash which is on chip.
第一级缓存是嵌入芯片中的缓存。
All the way.
一路走来。
If you are going to send a packet to communicate with someone in california
如果你要发送一个数据包与加利福尼亚的某人进行通信
to netherlands,
到荷兰
what?
什么？
It's 150 million seconds.
这是1.5亿秒。
So you need to handle a scale,
所以你需要处理一个称重器，
a difference in scale,
规模上的差异
in the range of what?
在什么范围内？
Eight order of magnitude more.
比原来多了八个数量级。
Basically,
基本上，
let me actually stop here and see what are the questions.
让我停下来看看有哪些问题。
Why does industry intel,
为什么工业情报
apple say the onslaught is not over?
苹果表示袭击尚未结束。
So the morse law from that very definition of the morse law,
因此，根据莫尔定律的定义，
it is pretty much over.
基本上已经结束了。
It's physical,
这是物理的。
right?
对的？
What they say is that what this company say,
他们所说的是这家公司所说的。
it's fundamentally look,
它基本上看起来是这样的
if the morse law,
如果摩尔定律，
if you say that the morse law is over and i'm building chips,
如果你说摩尔定律已经结束，而我正在制造芯片，
why would you build?
为什么要构建？
Why would you buy chips from me?
为什么你会从我这里购买芯片呢？
Because this means that the new chips will be the same like the old chips.
这意味着新芯片将与旧芯片相同。
No more power, right?
没有电了，对吗？
So there is a little bit also of,
所以还有一点点的，
they said,
他们说，
I cannot say that the morse law is,
我不能说摩尔定律是什么。
it's over,
结束了，
because the morse law is what the public associated with the performance.
因为摩尔定律是公众所关联的性能标志。
Right?
对吗？
So it's a little bit of also marketing.
所以这也有一点点营销的成分。
The more slow is over,
越慢就结束了
but the more slow it has a very precise definition.
但是"越慢"有一个非常精确的定义。
And these companies they talk to the public.
这些公司与公众进行交流。
And the public doesn't know the precise definition.
而且公众并不知道确切的定义。
Now, a small, slow means it means fast.
现在，一个小而慢的方式意味着快速。
Things become faster and faster.
事物变得越来越快。
Now, in truth, they use a lot of other techniques.
现在，实际上，他们使用了许多其他技术。
And we are going to talk about those in order to improve the performance.
我们将讨论这些问题以提高性能。
Right?
对吗？
And this is very visible in your iphone or in your android phone.
这在你的iPhone或Android手机上非常明显。
We'll talk a little bit about how they do it,
我们将稍微谈一下他们是如何做到的。
but that is not by improving necessary.
但这并不是通过改进所必需的。
The performance of a single core is by adding gp us,
单个核心的性能是通过添加GPU来提升的。
neural engines,
神经引擎
adding more course,
添加更多的课程
things like that.
诸如此类的事情。
We'll talk more about it.
我们会进一步讨论这个问题。
But good question.
但是好问题。
There are programs like spark and made videos that allow us to use
有一些像Spark和Made Videos这样的程序，可以让我们使用。
networks or computers to process a parallel workload.
网络或计算机用于处理并行工作负载。
But would it be feasible to create some type of operating system
但是创建某种类型的操作系统是否可行呢？
of software that could string together resources of multiple
能够将多个资源组合起来的软件。
computers for personal consumer use?
个人消费者使用的计算机？
I think
我认为
the question is it's a distributed operating system.
这是一个分布式操作系统。
I think that there is not a coherent operating system,
我认为目前还没有一个完整的操作系统。
but the elements of a operating system dispute operating system
但是操作系统的要素与操作系统之间存在争议。
are already there.
已经在那里了。
Because one thing can you probably know about cuba net is cabernet is
因为有一件事你可能知道关于古巴网络，那就是卡贝尔纳特（Cabernet）是其中之一。
provides resource orchestration,
提供资源编排功能，
resource management over multiple machines, over a cluster.
在集群中跨多台机器进行资源管理。
That's one.
这是一个。
The now that then you have distributed file systems,
现在，你已经拥有分布式文件系统了。
right?
对的？
Like hdfs or you have these blob stores like,
像HDFS这样的分布式文件系统，或者你有类似的Blob存储。
i'm as I double ss three.
我是I double ss three。
We'll talk more to towards the end of the class.
我们会在课程结束前更多地交流。
It's a good question.
这是一个很好的问题。
Probably you should expect that at some point,
也许你应该预计在某个时候，
you are going to see this kind of pieces coming
你将会看到这样的作品出现。
together in a more coherent way in what you could call
以一种更连贯的方式共同合作，你可以称之为
a distributed operating system.
一个分布式操作系统。
So fundamentally,
因此，从根本上说，
it's again.
又是你。
So why things are exciting?
为什么事情会令人兴奋呢？
Because they are challenging.
因为它们具有挑战性。
Why are things challenging?
为什么事情会具有挑战性？
Because they are complex.
因为它们很复杂。
And this complexity,
而且这种复杂性，
it's growing fast.
它正在快速增长。
Why is complexity growing?
为什么复杂性在增加？
Because you have the demands of the new application
因为你有新应用的需求
are growing faster than ever.
正在以前所未有的速度增长。
Capabilities of us of the harder are no longer growing like they used to be.
我们对硬件的使用能力不再像过去那样增长。
So then you need to add to innovate on the architecture.
那么你需要在架构上进行创新。
You have different specialized chips.
你有不同的专用芯片。
You need to distribute these applications.
你需要分发这些应用程序。
You need to parallelize the programs and many more.
你需要将程序并行化，还有许多其他任务。
And i'll talk a little more about it.
我会再多谈一些关于它的内容。
And then the applications themselves are more complicated.
而且应用程序本身更加复杂。
The application goes to have a variety of software modules.
该应用程序将具有多种软件模块。
And we'll talk more about that.
我们将会更详细地讨论这个问题。
But remember,
但请记住，
if you have almost every application you are using today is not running
如果你使用的几乎每个应用程序都无法运行
on only on your machine,
仅限于您的机器上，
it has a back and use facebook.
它有一个背面并且使用Facebook。
A lot of things happen in the back and use google
很多事情都是在后台发生的，使用谷歌。
or any other google applications and80% is into the backup.
或任何其他谷歌应用程序，其中80%用于备份。
Do it at everything almost right net flicks name it.
几乎所有的事情都可以在网飞上找到，名字就叫它。
Right?
对吗？
And then it has to run a different heart of architectures.
然后它必须运行不同的体系结构。
And because of the more slow has ended,
由于速度较慢，已经结束了。
you are going to have or to see a proliferation.
你将会经历或见证一场激增。
You are already seeing a proliferation of hardware architectures.
你已经看到了硬件架构的大量增加。
Just to give you an example here,
只是为了给你举个例子，
and it's a personal example when he started spark and he started in 2009.
这是一个个人的例子，他在2009年开始使用Spark。
So what 12 years ago,
那么，12年前发生了什么？
we are focusing only for processing data,
我们只关注数据处理。
which is in the memory efficiently,
在内存中高效的是哪个？
and we are focusing only on cp us.
我们只关注中央处理器（CPU）。
Right?
对吗？
It's like we assume that the processing is done by the general purpose,
这就好像我们假设处理是由通用目的的设备完成的。
proposed processors that I end up when he started ray,
当他开始使用光线追踪时，我提议使用的处理器是
which was that was happening like in 2016.
这是发生在2016年的事情。
So it's after only67 years,
所以只过了67年，
we already have to take into account and to design it
我们已经必须考虑并设计它。
for heterogeneous harder to handle gp us at that time.
在那个时候，对于异构的GPU来说更难处理。
Now, to handle gp us and so forth, this is real.
现在，处理图形处理器等等，这是真实的。
Obviously, this comes with additional complexity.
显然，这会带来额外的复杂性。
It's once you are over the network,
一旦你连接到网络上，
you are also exposed to attacks.
你也会受到攻击的威胁。
And this means that because heterogeneity is increasing dramatically,
这意味着由于异质性急剧增加，
that the operating system becomes even more important,
操作系统变得更加重要，
because it's much harder to extract them away.
因为将它们分离出来要困难得多。
Right?
对吗？
Because if you don't ask like the way,
因为如果你不以这种方式提问，
it's very hard to write applications,
编写应用程序非常困难，
and the operating system is one of the key roles, like we discussed,
操作系统是其中一个关键角色，正如我们所讨论的那样，
is to make that writing developing application very easy.
是使编写开发应用程序变得非常简单。
Right?
对吗？
That's why it's operating.
这就是为什么它在运行。
Some are more challenging,
有些更具挑战性，
are more needed than ever.
比以往任何时候都更加需要。
Now, we discussed and they only discussed about specialized hardware.
现在，我们讨论了一下，他们只讨论了专用硬件的问题。
I mentioned that it's not only specialized hardware.
我提到了这不仅仅是专门的硬件。
How people try to go around the more slow or kind of so to speak extend
人们如何绕过更慢或者可以说是延长的问题
in terms of performance.
从性能方面来看。
In other ways,
在其他方面，
are having more and more courts,
越来越多的法院。
even for general proposed processors,
即使对于一般提出的处理器来说，
like intelligent five that has a processor is 64 course.
像智能五一样，它具有64位处理器。
I am the epic, the same 64 course,
我是史诗级的，同样是64课程。
although there are rumors that the new version will have 128 course.
尽管有传言称新版本将有128门课程。
If you look at these processors,
如果你看一下这些处理器，
actually they are them complicated.
实际上它们是相当复杂的。
Right?
对吗？
This is how it looks like.
这是它的外观。
You have a bunch,
你有一堆东西。
you have cash,
你有现金。
you have some other components to manage memory.
你还有其他组件来管理内存。
You have other components here down to can also
你还有其他组件在这里，可以继续使用。
control the io input output,
控制输入输出(IO)。
getting the data in and out of the processor.
将数据输入和输出处理器。
And reading from the memory,
从内存中读取数据，
which is not on the cheap, it's off the cheap.
这不是便宜的，而是贵的。
You have also in many systems,
在许多系统中，你也有
you have processor,
你有处理器。
you have some integrated graphics.
你的电脑有一些集成显卡。
Right?
对吗？
This is a trend which come and sorry,
这是一个来了又去的趋势，很抱歉。
if you look under the hood,
如果你仔细观察一下内部结构，
they are connected.
它们已连接。
It's like mini system in miniature.
它就像是一个微型系统。
Right?
对吗？
In this case, you are going to have this is a corpus or car.
在这种情况下，你将拥有一个语料库或汽车。
Now you are connected to different airports,
现在你已经连接到不同的机场了，
memory and many other things.
内存和许多其他东西。
And this complexity just increasing.
而且这种复杂性还在不断增加。
So here down is like it's what we are seeing.
下面这里就像是我们所看到的。
Here is another trend.
这是另一个趋势。
It's system on a chip,
这是系统级芯片（SoC）。
right?
对的？
And when going back to that question and apple say, maybe say is more slow,
当回到那个问题并且苹果说，也许说得更慢一些，
is not done.
还没有完成。
This is what they do.
这是他们所做的事情。
And how they sustain the increasing performance again,
以及他们如何再次提高性能的持续性，
which is not necessarily later is a morse law,
不一定晚于莫尔斯定律的是什么
is putting more and more intelligence,
是将越来越多的智能化技术应用于
more and more functionality on the same chip.
在同一芯片上实现越来越多的功能。
Right?
对吗？
Here, I will show you have not only cp us,
在这里，我将向你展示不仅仅是复制我们的能力，
and the cpu have multiple cores.
而且CPU拥有多个核心。
I'd be sent or eight between six and ten,
我会在六点到十点之间发送或回复信息。
but you have gps right?
但是你有GPS吗？
Integrated on the same chip.
集成在同一芯片上。
You have a core gp us,
您有一个核心的GPU。
right?
对的？
A core cp us.
一个核心的中央处理器。
And in addition to that,
除此之外，
you have no oral engine,
你没有口语引擎。
which is really focused on neural to supporting machine learning workloads,
这个系统真正专注于支持机器学习工作负载的神经网络。
the newer land or water blocks.
更新的陆地或水域方块。
Right?
对吗？
This is the things which are like your fingerprint sensor,
这是类似于指纹传感器的东西。
or recognizing as your face using your face to unlock the phone.
或者通过识别你的脸来解锁手机。
Right?
对吗？
Face recognition.
人脸识别。
Right?
对吗？
That's how you are going to get more performance.
这是你如何获得更高性能的方法。
The code is also very complicated,
代码也非常复杂，
is growing in complexity.
正在变得越来越复杂。
And I don't have the numbers more recent numbers,
我没有更近期的数据。
but here is a vista.
但是这里有一个问题。
This one15 years ago called it was what?
15年前叫它是什么？
50 millions code lines of code is huge complexity.
5000万行代码是巨大的复杂性。
Just to give you a sense of nasa space shuttle,
只是为了让你对NASA的航天飞机有个概念，
you remember, it was a space shuttle,
你记得，那是一艘航天飞机，
is no longer in service.
不再提供服务。
It has what?
它有什么？
I don't know, one of the millions lines of code is crazy.
我不知道，其中的一行代码是疯狂的。
And then it's, again, like I mentioned several times,
然后，就像我多次提到的那样，
you have to scale everyone to,
你需要将每个人的规模缩放到...
because you can no longer do these workloads on a single noun,
因为你不能再在一个单一的名词上完成这些工作负载了。
on a single machine.
在一台单机上。
Like I show you the data for machine learning workloads,
我给你展示机器学习工作负载的数据，
the same thing is for big data analytics,
同样的情况也适用于大数据分析。
scientific computing.
科学计算。
You have so we have several computers which are parallel computers
你好，我们有几台并行计算机。
or indispensable computer since 80s to support this kind of work.
自80年代以来，计算机已成为支持这种工作的不可或缺的工具。
And then on top of that,
而且除此之外，
everything is connected.
一切都相互关联。
This is the internet.
这是互联网。
Probably the most and the most impressive artifact.
可能是最令人印象深刻的文物。
The humans have created.
人类创造了。
Right?
对吗？
It links the entire world,
它连接了整个世界，
right?
对的？
And is what you have 4.5 billions people connected to the internet.
你说的是全球有45亿人连接到互联网吗？
This is what this plot shelves.
这是这个图表所展示的内容。
Right?
对吗？
And this is what is it happens only25 years.
这只发生了25年。
It's quite amazing.
这真是太令人惊叹了。
And then the smartphone shipments exceeded the pc shipments,
然后智能手机的出货量超过了个人电脑的出货量。
what I think in200011.
200011年我所思考的是什么。
And today,
今天，
right today actually turns out that you have close to 4
今天事实上你接近于4
billion smartphones and 5 point something billions mobile phones.
十亿部智能手机和五十多亿部移动电话。
Right?
对吗？
This data is a little bit old.
这些数据有点旧了。
And all of those all the phones are connected.
所有这些手机都已连接。
So you have 4 billion,
所以你有40亿。
this kind of very powerful devices at the end of the day which are connected.
这种非常强大的设备最终都是相互连接的。
You have everything,
你拥有一切，
you have a huge range, right?
你有一个很大的范围，对吗？
You have everything from data centered with hundreds of thousands
你拥有数十万个数据中心的一切
of computers to sends on others,
将计算机上的信息发送给其他计算机
right?
对的？
Which you may not be even able to see these chips,
你可能甚至看不到这些芯片，
right?
对的？
And everything in between,
以及中间的一切，
right?
对的？
And different or close.
不同或相似。
And just to drive home the.and i'll here.
为了强调一下，我会在这里。
So just like I mentioned earlier,
就像我之前提到的那样，
many of the applications you are using today,
你今天使用的许多应用程序，
they are distributed,
它们是分布式的。
right?
对的？
Facebook, twitter, and so forth.
Facebook、Twitter等等。
And this is what happens under the hood.
这就是在底层发生的事情。
Right?
对吗？
And let's say you do a simple search,
假设你进行了一个简单的搜索，
right?
对的？
From your android phone or iphone.
从您的安卓手机或iPhone上。
Right?
对吗？
What do you do?
你做什么工作？
So first of all,
首先，
you need to figure out were back and were servers you need to connect,
你需要找出我们的后端和服务器需要连接的位置。
to get to send the request,
发送请求的方法是：
your search request, to get the answer.
您的搜索请求，以获取答案。
In order to do that,
为了做到这一点，
you need to do this.
你需要做这个。
Dns request, domain, name,
DNS请求，域名，名称
salaries.
工资。
Right?
对吗？
And it's like you need to resolve use this link, right?
是的，你需要使用这个链接来解决问题，对吗？
It's google dot com to a particular server.
这是将网址"google.com"发送到特定服务器。
You have an entire domain,
你拥有一个完整的域名，
dns infrastructure,
DNS基础设施
which consisting of many servers,
由许多服务器组成的
they will cooperate to give you an answer,
他们会合作给你一个答案。
to tell you who you need to connect to,
告诉你需要连接的人
who you need to send the pakistan.
你需要将资料发送给巴基斯坦。
Now, when you get that address,
现在，当你获得那个地址时，
which is an ip address,
哪个是一个IP地址？
you are going to send it over the internet, right?
你打算通过互联网发送吗？
Over the internet,
通过互联网
these packets are going to be rooted by switches, routers, and so forth.
这些数据包将会通过交换机、路由器等设备进行路由。
And it's going to go based on the ip address,
它将根据IP地址进行操作。
probably in a data center,
可能在一个数据中心中，
they are going to learn to a load balancer.
他们将要学习负载均衡器。
The loud balancer, you get the packets you send to a server,
负载均衡器，你会收到发送给服务器的数据包。
the web server,
网络服务器，
probably the web server is going to look at the request.
可能是Web服务器要查看请求。
And based on the request is going to send
根据请求即将发送的内容
request an entire other disciplinary systems
to resolve that request.
Right?
To give you the answers.
If you have a google inquiry,
obviously, you may also have to get some ads in the result in the process.
You have another infrastructure doing only that,
figuring out what as the shelf.
And then you need to put together the entire page and send it
back and to be displayed on your computer.
This is just to give you a sense how complicated things are.
And all of these interactions are handled by the operating system.
Right?
At the lower level.
Let me just,
we have only 5 minutes.
So what i'm going to do,
i'm going to do the following thing,
and we are going to continue next time.
Let me first try to answer some of the question,
and then i'm going to go straight to some logistics.
How low level does this class get?
Do it talk about things like pipelining?
We want to talk much about like pipelining.
If you are referring as the cpu process in the cpu pipelining,
like instruction pipelining,
we are going to talk a little bit about hyper threading.
We are going to talk about that.
We'll answer.
This is about hyper threading.
We are going to talk more about being short.
It's a way in which you can share the core,
one core between two threads,
which can be come from different applications.
So it's multiplexing one core.
So let me just skip,
and obviously,
we'll do that as next time and talk a little bit here,
more about the class syllabus.
And it's online.
You have the class.
So we are going to, obviously,
to learn the operating system concepts and how a system programmer
is going to use these concepts.
What are the interfaces?
Ap is?
Then we are going to learn about how the operating system implements a lot
some of this functionality.
Like how is going to manage concurrency,
multiple applications,
accessing share resources at the same time,
address space,
how you are going to provide isolation between different applications.
So that each one application or process will not step over the memory
of another application or process.
File systems,
how you are going to access and store the data and retrieve the data,
send the data and receive the data over the network.
We are going to talk a little bit about disability systems
and the protocols which are and the mechanics which are implemented
by the distributed systems to make them easier to use and to be more
efficient.
And we are going to talk about reliability and security for tolerance,
protection, and so forth.
Finally,
we are going to talk about a little bit about cloud infrastructure,
which is very relevant, because right now,
cloud is the effect of standard.
You are going to.
Many companies are building,
especially startups are building their application.
This class is hands on.
You are going to learn by doing.
You have a bunch of homeworks and projects are extremely important.
And with the projects you are going to implement,
actually also in the homework,
some mechanism, some functionality that operating system,
though I like your strength and scheduling file systems,
and so forth, memory allocation.
This will be very exciting.
Now, what are the demands?
The project will require you to be
very comfortable with programming and debugging c so remember,
recall pointers,
memory management,
use gdp for debugging.
So just go over 61 c again,
you need to know how to use git for version control.
There is ac programming reference here if you need.
So please consult that.
I think the first section are dedicated to programming and debugging reviews.
So please attend these sections.
You can attend it to section, I believe,
for the first 2 weeks after that,
you need to choose one session a section.
The other thing I want to say and to be quite quick here,
but also I want to emphasize that projects are very important,
and projects are not only about doing a piece of software and building
a piece of software,
but project about teaching you how to collaborate,
how to work in a team.
This will be extremely important for you.
If you go and to join to be a software engineer,
this is a key skill you need to learn.
You are going to learn to do to work in a team.
You need to make the team successful,
because that's that's how you are going to become successful.
You are not going to work alone.
We require the project to have four members,
never five.
The exception will be very rare.
Please, this is pandemic.
Still, pandemic is very hard, more active.
Most of the activities will be online.
If you do online,
turn the camera on,
try to emulate the physical presence as much as possible.
But also now you can also the campus is open.
Right?
If you feel comfortable,
you can go and meet in paris.
Right?
But collaborate,
right?
And also not only between yours,
your man, you and your members of team,
but also your da right?
Over communication is how you make this project successful.
Then you need to devise the work among the members of the team,
right?
To require both decision and additional collaboration,
because every you are going to depend on the work of other people in your team.
This is a grading.
36% is for 3 meters.
We have only meters.
Now, final,
36% projects,
80% homeworks,
10% participation, section, lectures, and so forth.
You'll hear more about the project.
You have a design document.
Design document will be due.
You are going to get feedback from the t as and so forth.
Books and infrastructures,
you should be able to find all the Information as a class web page.
There is a piazza.
You find the link to the piazza as well.
There the lectures will be recorded.
Sorry, about today,
about the beginning of the lecture.
The textbook is the operating system principles and practice
from Tom Anderson and Tom Anderson and Mike darling.
There are a few other books, very good,
and you are encouraged to consult and to,
you can refer to.
And we are going to have a few supplemental materials,
a few research papers, and so forth.
We are going to let.
Finally,
Lee's is like,
this is not no joke.
Personal integrity.
You sign there used to be academic honor code.
So please leave by it.
You can explain the concept of other people in the group.
You can discuss the concept with other people on the group.
You can even help your friend to debug your code, the code,
or you can search online for generic codes.
This is no good,
but you cannot share the code with other groups.
You cannot copy or read another group's code or best cases.
You cannot call to copy or reading online code or test cases from prior years.
And we are going that we compare all projects submission against priority
of emissions and online solutions
and will take actions right against your friend.
So please don't do that.
Is not going to help you to with learning.
That's probably the most important reason you shouldn't do it.
Let's try hard to make this class in to keep this class interactive.
I'm going to stop here.
I'm going to take it about the talker.
Obviously,
a little bit more about the operating system general overview next time.
Now let me answer the questions which are still here.
How there are two other questions.
There is actually one last question.
Would it be good to review material of the later half of six times c
like absolutely components of the CPU how much of this?
Absolutely?
This would be very useful?
We are going to talk about cashing.
We are going to talk and reviewing that.
It will be so useful.
How does a participation grading work?
This will be mostly because it will be a more smaller groups from interacting
with your t as office hours and discussions,
discussion sections.
I am at the size of this class.
I don't think I will have the opportunity to interact with many of you,
especially since we are remote.
But obviously, if you have any problem, anything,
please do not hesitate to drop me an EMAIL.
And you can look for me,
i'll be in a soda hall,
at least now and then.
Thank you so much, everyone.
And i'll see you next Tuesday.
If you have any other questions,
please ask the questions.
If you also have any other suggestions about how to make the class better?
More interactive, please don't know how to hesitate to let us know.
It's again, II the first time I'm using is a seminar,
a it's hard to just talk at the screen and see the slide,
not see any of your faces.
But let's try to do our best and any idea.
You see, you have to improve interactivity to improve the class.
In general, let us know.
Thank you.